Caffè Lena collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 3: Graphic Materials
  - Subseries 4: Photos by other photographers, circa 1960s-2006
    - Photos by Howard Eskin - general (1 of 2), 1998-2005 (Box-folder 25/9)
      Photos are 4 in x 6 in. The majority are in color, and show performers in concert.
    - Photos by Howard Eskin - general (2 of 2), 1998-2005 (Box-folder 25/10)
      See note for 26/9.
    - Photos by Howard Eskin - Caffè Lena: recent history, circa 2006 (Box-folder 25/11)
  - Subseries 5: Exhibit images and art works, circa 1960s-2004
    - Sub-subseries 1: Exhibit images
      13 black-and-white and 5 color photos affixed to foam core, probably for an exhibit circa 2006. Images range in size from approximately 3 in. x 4 1/2 in. to 6 3/4 in. x 10 in. Subjects include performers in concert at Caffè Lena and elsewhere, as well as portraits.
      - Gordon and Sharon Boyd's wedding party at Caffè Lena, October 8, 1971 (Box 26/1)
        Two color photos, plus an exhibit sign when the photos were on display.
      - Color images (Box 26/2)
        One photo of Lena Spencer in the kitchen; two photos of performers playing at Caffè Lena.
      - Black and white images (1 of 3) (Box 26/3)
        Images of performers playing or posing, people in Caffè Lena, and photos at various locations.
      - Black and white images (2 of 3) (Box 26/4)
        See note for 27/1.
      - Black and white images (3 of 3) (Box 26/5)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Art works
      - Art works by various artists; four are mounted on foam core. Images range in size from approximately 6 in. x 4 3/4 in. to 8 1/2 in. x 11 in. circa 1988-2004 (Box 26/6)
        6 items; different sizes, with most in black and white. Various art works paying tribute to Caffè Lena and Lena Spencer and, in one case, advertising an event.
  - Subseries 6: Oversize graphic materials, circa 1960s-1989, undated
    - Black and white photographs, circa 1960s (Box-folder 27/1)
      - Pete Seeger, 1962, 8 in. x 12 in.
        Photographed by Joe Alper.
      - Exterior of Caffè Lena, 8 in. x 12 in.
        Photographed by Craig Sweet.
      - Lena Spencer, 8 in. x 12 in.
      - Lena Spencer sitting in Caffè Lena, with a white cat sitting on a table, 11 in. x 13 3/4 in.
    - Contact sheets and multi-image sheets (Box-folder 27/2)
      - Photos by Dan Stetkar, 1962
        1 sheet of plain paper with 3 in. x 3 1/4 in. prints of black and white images. Sheet measures 11 in. x 14 in.
      - Photos by Dan Stetkar, 1989
        Four sheets of plain paper with black and white prints of contact sheets. Sheets measure 10 in. x 12 in.
      - Photos of Lena Spencer and others at an event, 1989 or before
        One sheet of color photos, each image measuring 4 1/2 in. x 5 in.
    - Publicity and related materials (Box-folder 27/3)
      All items are 20 in. x 14 in. or smaller. Includes publicity posters for the bands Bitchin' Babes (signed), Wicky Sears, and Three Guitars and a Mandolin (benefit concert for Ed Harris), small publicity posters for Caffè Lena, and a hand-drawn mock-up for renovation work on Caffè Lena.
    - Powerhouse Arena (Brooklyn, New York book store): publicity posters (Box-folder 27/4)
      One folder with two posters, each measure approximately 24 in. x 24 in.; one is a blow-up image of Bob Dylan, taken by Joe Alper, and the other is a calendar of events, including a scheduled book lunch for the book Caffè Lena: Inside America's Legendary Folk Music Coffeehouse, by Jocelyn Arem, featuring photos by Joe Alper.
- Series 4: Moving Images
  MV01-11, MV14, and MV16 were discovered to be audio-only items after they were numbered. They have been renumbered SR518-530. The previously-used MV numbers have not been reassigned.
  - "The Water Plan," circa 1960s, 1 film reel (1100 ft.): sound, color; 16 mm tail sync print (answer print). (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV18)
    May be a documentary about a dam project and the environmental impact that would result from its creation.
  - John Phillips and his Pickup Band, 1985 or before (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV12)
    Original ID number LENAA015. John is introduced as Papa John Phillips. The recording cuts away abruptly at about 01:33:00 to commercials and a segment of the movie "Back to the Future."
  - Interview with Lena Spencer, August 10, 1989, 1 videocassette (U-Matic, 00:10:52): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV13)
    Part of an interview with Lena Spencer. Recording begins with clips of a male singer onstage at Caffè Lena.
  - Voices on the Wind, with Beth Jochum, Brenda Fisher and Jude Klucitas, April 24, 1992, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV27)
  - Folk-A-Thon report, July 8, 1994, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV28)
    Broadcast on Channel 13, 11:05 p.m.
  - Frank Porter on In Tune, August 2, 1998, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV21)
  - An evening at Caffè Lena: Phil Henry, Nelson Shapiro, Brendan Coyle, March 29, 2000, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV24)
  - "Caffè Lena revisited": Phil Henry, Brendan Coyle, and Nelson Shapiro at Caffè Lena, September 24, 2000, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV29)
    Segment provided by Channel 10, Ticonderoga, NY TV.
  - Dave Carter night at Caffè Lena, May 10, 2003, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV26)
  - News magazine story on "No Direction Home" (documentary), September 29, 2005, 1 videocassette (VHS, 28 min., 2 sec.): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV17)
    InSight (program), copyright 2005 WMHT Educational Telecommunications, Albany NY. A look at Bob Dylan's impact on the local Saratoga Springs community and his relationship with photographer Elliott Landy. Marianne Potter interviews Landy. Jocelyn Arem speaks briefly.
  - Bob Dylan 70th Birthday Tribute / Caffè Lena 51st Anniversary Concert, May 21, 2011, 1 videodisc (DVD-R, 59 min., 6 sec.): sound, color. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV19)
    Various performer doing cover versions of Bob Dylan songs. MV19 and MV20 in this collection may have the same content.
  - Bob Dylan 70th Birthday Tribute / Caffè Lena 51st Anniversary Concert, May 21, 2011, 1 videodisc (DVD-R): sound, color. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV20)
  - Rick and friends at Caffè Lena, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV22)
  - Ira Bernstein, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV25)
  - Lena's chronicle (Saratoga tape), 1 videocassette (VHS): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV23)
  - Utah Phillips, 1 videocassette (VHS, 26 min., 21 sec.): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV15)
    Phillips sings and talks between songs.
  - Rory Block; unidentified male singer, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV31)
  - MSNBC, 1 videocassette (VHS): analog. (Item id AFC 2009/035: MV30)
    News stories with no direct relationship to the collection.
- Series 5: Artifacts
  - Three t-shirts, 1990, circa 2000s (Box 28)
    Two t-shirts date from circa 1990: a small red t-shirt and an x-large white t-shirt, both with an image in black of Lena Spencer and her Siamese cat, Sasha. These are accompanied by a letter from Dirk Westervelt, explaining the history of the t-shirts (as a fundraiser to keep Caffè Lena in business after Lena's death). The third t-shirt is large, in black with a colorful design on the back depicting the Caffè Lena building front and the motto "good folk since 1960." The front of the t-shirt has a smaller design, in white with black letters: "Lunch at the Ritz Studios / Beekman Street Galleries."
Bibliography
Arem, Jocelyn, in collaboration with Caffè Lena. Caffè Lena: Inside America's Legendary Folk Music Coffeehouse. Brooklyn, NY: powerHouse Books, 2013.